The Carleton Hodge collection: books from the library of Carleton Hodge Z7770 .H6
Lilly Library
The Carleton Hodge collection: books from the library of Carleton Hodge
1805-1995
Lilly Library
Z7770 .H6
56 Boxes
Consists of personal collection of Professor Carleton Hodge, including many 19th and 20th century Bibles and works about the Bible.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Carleton T. Hodge, Professor Emeritus of Linguistics and Anthropology at Indiana University, was born in Springfield, Illinois on November 27, 1917 and died on September 8, 1998. After receiving his B.A. in 1939 from DePauw University, he began graduate work in linguistics, Near Eastern studies, and Ancient Egyptian at the University of Pennsylvania. He completed his Ph.D. dissertation, a descriptive grammar of Hausa, in 1943. From 1943 to 1963, Hodge worked for the Foreign Service Institute, supervising courses in foreign language training and publishing pedagogical language materials such as Some Aspects of Persian Style (1957) and Serbo-Croatian Stress and Pitch (1958).
In 1964, Hodge took a tenured position at Indiana University where he remained until his retirement in 1983. Hodge taught linguistics and was a founding member of both the Department of Linguistics and the African Studies Program, where he served on various committees throughout his career. He was the director of the Intensive Language Training Center, where he negotiated contracts with the Peace Corps and the Office of Education, until 1968. From 1969-1972, Hodge served as Associate Chairman of the Research Center for the Language Sciences and was Editor-in-Chief of the African Series, a role he continued after leaving the RCLS. Hodge then went on to teach linguistics full time and to hold a joint appointment in Linguistics and Anthropology.
After his retirement from Indiana University in 1983, Hodge continued to publish articles and book reviews. A full bibliography of his writings lists over 150 publications. Hodge also continued to attend meetings of the Linguistic Society of America, the American Oriental Society, and the Linguistic Society of India. Throughout his career, Hodge made both practical teaching and research contributions on the grammar and historical relationships among the languages of Africa, Europe, and Asia.
Carleton T. Hodge died in Bloomington, Indiana on September 8, 1998. He was survived by his wife, Pat (Sutcliffe) Hodge; four children: daughter Nina, and sons Philip, Nicholas, and Charles; and two grandchildren.
Arrangement
Books are arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of personal collection of Professor Carleton Hodge, including many 19th and 20th century Bibles and works about the Bible.
Related Material
See the Carleton T. Hodge papers at the Indiana University Archives, Indiana University, Bloomington.
Hodge, C. T. (Carleton Taylor), 1917-1998--Library.; Bible.; Bible--Harmonies.; Hodge, C. T. (Carleton Taylor), 1917-1998
- A
  - Allis, Oswald T. Five books of Moses a reexamination of the modern theory that the Pentateuch is a late compilation from diverse and conflicting sources by authors and editors whose identity is completely unknown. Philadelphia: Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing Company, 1943 (Box 27)
  - Allis, Oswald T. God spake by Moses an exposition of the Pentateuch. [Sticker of the distributer over publisher information] Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Book House, 1951 (Box 28)
- B (Box 28)
  - Beauclerk, Henry. Jesus his life in the very words of the four Gospels a diatessaron. London: Burns and Oates, Limited, 1896 (Box 8)
  - Bible. (t.p. for O.T. is missing using N.T.) New Testament of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ: translated out of the original Greek: and with the former translations diligently compared and revised, by His Majesty's special command. Appointed to be read in churches. London: Eyre & Spottiswoode, [1800s?]. (Box 8)
  - Bible. Biblia, das ist die ganze heilige schrift des alten und neuen testaments, nach der deutschen uebersetzung D. Martin Luthers; mit eines jeden capitels kurzen Summarien, auch... Erste Auflage. Reading: Gottlob Jungmnn, 1805 (Box 22)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments: together with the Apocrypha: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised, by the special command of his Majesty King James I of England. With marginal notes and references... Philadelphia: Printed and Published by Mathew Carey, 1806 (Box 19)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments: together with the Apocrypha: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised; with marginal notes and references, and the explanatory notes of Osterv Ald... embellished with maps, and a number of elegant historical engravings. New York: Printed and sold by Collins, Perkins, and Co., 1806-1807 (N.T. t.p. has date of 1806) (Box 25)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments, together with the Apocrypha at large; and illustrated with notes and annotations, theological, practical and divine: the whole forming a neat family bible, embellished with thirty beautiful engravings. By the Rev. Mr. Ostervald, ... Stourbridge: printed and published by J. Heming, 1808 (Box 26)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, ... (center of page has a hole) with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Boston: Printed by Greenough and Stebbins, 1809 (Box 14)
  - Bible. Scripture expositor; a new commentary critical and practical, on the Holy Bible; in which difficult passages are explained, mistranslations corrected, and apparent contradictions reconciled, by reference to the labors of the most celebrated critics and commentators, ancient and modern; particularly to the treasures of eastern literature. ... by the Rev. Samuel Burder, A.M. ... In Two Volumes. London: Albion Press printed for J. and J. Cundee, [1811?] (Box 34)
    - Vol. I, pt. I. Genesis to end of Samuel 2 (Box 34)
    - Vol. I, pt. II. 1 Kings to end of Psalms (Box 34)
    - Vol. II, pt. I. Proverb to end of Malachi (Box 34)
    - Vol. II, pt. II. Matthew to end of Revelations (Box 34)
  - Bible. New family bible, containing the old and new testaments, with notes, illustrations, and practical improvements, selected from the exposition of the Rev. Matthew Henry. By the Rev. E. Bloomfield. Embellished with fifty beautiful engravings. Bungay: printed and published by C. Brightly and Co., published also by T. Kinnersley, 1811 (Box 26)
    - Vol. 1 (Box 26)
    - Vol. 2 (Box 26)
  - Bible. (O.T. title page missing. Using information from N.T. t.p.) Heilige Schrift neuen testaments unser herrr Jesu Christi, ferdeeutschet von Doktor Martin Luther; mit jeden capitels kurzen summarien und richtigen schriftstellen auf das duetlichste fersehen. Minden: Georg Wilhelm E?smann, 1811 (Box 38)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. London: Stereotyped for the Bible Society at Philadelphia, by T. Rutt, 1812 (Box 14)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. London: Stereotyped for the Bible Society at Philadelphia, by T. Rutt(No covers), 1812 (Box 38)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Boston: Printed for Thomas and Andrews, West and Richardson, and West and Blake by W. Greenough, 1814 (Box 14)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments, together with the Apocrypha: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised, by the special command of his majesty King James I of England. With marginal notes and references. To which are added... Philadelphia: Printed and Published by M. Carey, 1815 (Box 19)
  - Bible. Biblia, das ist die ganze heilige schrift des alten und neuen testaments, nach der deutschen uebersetzung D. Martin Luthers. Die CXX auflage. Halle: Cansteinischen Bibel – Anstalt, 1816 (Box 7)
  - Bible. Old testament translated out of the original Hebrew, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Together with the Apocrypha: done by the special command of King James I of England. Philadelphia: Printed and Published by M. Carey(T.p. for whole Bible missing; N.T. t.p. has same imprint information), 1816 (Box 19)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old & new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. With marginal notes and references. Together with the Apocrypha. ... Brattleborough, Vt.: J. Hollbrook's Stereotype Copy seventh edition, 1816-1817 (N.T. t.p. imprint 1816) (Box 50)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments, together with Apocrypha: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised, by the special command of his Majesty King James I of England. With marginal notes and references. ... Philadelphia: Printed and Published by M. Carey, 1816-1817 (N.T. t.p. imprint 1817) (Box 18)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Boston: Hudson and Co., 1817 (Box 14)
  - Bible. (O.T. t.p. is missing) Das Neue testament unsers HCrrn und Heilandes Jesu Christi, verdeutsch fon D. Martin Luther. Dreizehente Auflage. Stututtgart: mit ?ebenden Schriften dedrucht, und zu finden ben der privilegirten Bible = An?alt, 1821 (Box 22)
  - Bible. [Holbrook & Fessenden's stereotype hot-press edition.] The holy bible: containing the old & new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised, with marginal notes and references. ... Brattleborough, Vt.: Holbrook & Fessenden, 1821 (Box 49)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments. Translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Philadelphia: Stereotyped by D. & G. Bruce, 1821-1823 (N.T. imprint date 1821) (Box 12)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Philadelphia: H.C. Carey & I. Lea, 1823 (Box 16)
  - Bible. Kimber and Sharpless' Stereotype edition. The Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: together with the Apocrypha: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. With Canne's marginal notes and references. ... Stereotyped by E. White, New-York. Philadelphia: Kimber and Sharpless, [1823-1844?] (Date range from a note by Hodge) (Box 52)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. New York: stereotyped for the American Bible Society by D. & G. Bruce, 1824 (Box 14)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, translated from the Latin vulagt: diligently compared with the Hebrew, Greek, and other editions, in divers languages. The Old Testament, first published by the English College at Doway, A.D. 1609. and New Testament, first published by the English College at Rhemes, A.D. 1582. ... First stereotype, from the fifth Dublin edition. ... Philadelphia: Eugene Cummiskey, 1824 (Box 38)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, translated from the Latin vulagt: diligently compared with the Hebrew, Greek, and other editions, in divers languages. The Old Testament, first published by the English College at Doway, A.D. 1609. and New Testament, first published by the English College at Rhemes, A.D. 1582. ... First stereotype, from the fifth Dublin edition. ... Philadelphia: Eugene Cummiskey, 1824-1831 (date on N.T. t.p. 1831) (Box 38)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. With Canne's marginal notes and references. To which are added an index: and an alphabetical table of all the names in the old and new testaments with their significations. ... Stereotyped for Collins and Co. by B. & J. Collins. Boston: Published by C. Ewer and T. Bedlington, 1825 (Box 42)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments; translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Philadelphia: Published by George W. Mentz, 1826 (Box 12)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. With Canne's marginal notes and references together with the apocrypha. ... Boston: Published by C. Ewer and T. Bedlington, printed by J.H.A. Frost, 1827 (Box 13)
  - Bible. Stereotype edition. The Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: together with the Apocrypha: translated out of the original tongues: and with the former translations diligently compared and revised with copious marginal notes and references. To which are added, an index; an alphabetical table... [imprint information missing from O.T. t.p. information missing from O.T. t.p. information taken from N.T. t.p.] [Cooperstown: Printed by H. & E. Phinney for S. Thompson, York, (U.C.), 1827] (Box 40)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments; translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Philadelphia: Published by George W. Mentz, 1827 (Box 12)
  - Bible. Biblia, das ist die ganze heilige schrift des alten und neuen testaments, nach der deutschen uebersetzung D. Martin Luthers; mit eines jeden capitels kurzen Summarien, … Philadelphia: Kimber und Scharlpes, 1828 (Box 7)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. New York: Stereotyped for the American Bible Society by D. & G. Bruce, 1828 (Box 13)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: together with the Apocrypha: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. With Canne's marginal notes and references. ... New York: Daniel D. Smith, 1828 (Box 13)
  - Bible. Biblia, das ist: die ganze heilige schrift des alten und neuen testaments, nach der deutschen uebersetzung D. Martin Luthers; mit eines jeden capitels kurzen Summarien, ... Philadelphia: In Stereotypen versertigt, von J. Howe, Kimber und Scharlpes Buchhandler, 1828 (Box 21)
  - Bible. H. & E. Phinney's Stereotype edition The Holy Bible containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised with Canne's marginal notes and references. To which are added ... Cooperstown, N.Y.: Stereotyped, Printed and Published by H. & E. Phinney(No covers)., 1829 (Box 21)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. New York: Stereotyped by James Conner, for the American Bible Society, 1830 (Box 13)
  - Bible. Biblia, das ist die ganze heilige schrift des alten und neuen testaments, nach der deutschen uebersetzung D. Martin Luthers; mit eines jeden capitels kurzen Summarien, ... Philadelphia: Kimber und Scharlpes, 1830 (Box 7)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. New York: Printed by D. Fanshaw, for the American Bible Society, 1830 (Box 13)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues: and with the former translations diligently compared and revised, by His Majesty's Special Command. Appointed to be read in churches. Cambridge: Printed by J. Smith, Printer to the University. For the British and Foreign Bible Society, 1830 (Box 40)
  - Bible. English version of the Pollyglott Bible; containing the old and new testaments: with a copious and original selection of references to parallel and illustrative passages, exhibited in a manner hitherto unattempted. London: Printed for Samuel Bagster(In English and Hebrew) (Only the old Testament is present)., 1831 (Box 22)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. With Canne's marginal notes and references... Stereotyped by B. & J. Collins. Boston: Langdon Coffin, 1831 (Box 48)
  - Bible. Daniel D. Smith's stereotype edition. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments, translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised with Canne's marginal notes and references: ... stereotyped by J. Howe, Philadelphia. New York: Daniel D. Smith, 1832 (Box 37)
  - Bible. H. & E. Phinney's stereotype edition the Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised with Canne's marginal notes and references. ... Cooperstown, (N.Y.): Stereotyped, printed and published by H. & E. Phinney, 1834 (Box 40)
  - Bible. Fessendon & Co's edition. The English version of the polyglot bible, containing the old and new testaments, with the marginal readings, and a full and original selection of references to parallel and illustrative passages, ... Brattleboro: Fessendon & Co. and Peck & Wood, and Boston: sold by Lincoln, Edmands & Co. and William Peirce, 1834 (Box 42)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Hartford, CT: Andrus & Judd, 1835 (Box 12)
  - Bible. Holy Bible: containing the old and new testaments: together with the Apocrypha: translated out of the original tongues. and with the former translations diligently compared and revised; with Canne's marginal notes and references. To which are added, an index; ... Woodstock, VT: N. Haskell, 1836 (Box 52)
  - Bible. English version of the polyglot bible, containing the old and new testaments; with the marginal readings: together with a copious and original selection of references to parallel and illustrative passages. Exhibited in a manner hitherto unattempted. Philadelphia: stereotyped by L. Johnson Published by Desilver, Thomas & Co., 1837 (Box 20)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Claremont, N.H.: Claremont Manufacturing Company's Power Press, 1838 (Box 12)
  - Bible. Holy Bible; containing the old and new testaments, according to the authorized version; with the references and marginal readings of the polyglot bible, with numerous additions from Bagster's comprehensive bible. First edition. Hartford, Con.: Andrus, Judd, & Franklin, 1838 (Box 52)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues: and with the former translations diligently compared and revised: with references and various readings. Illustrated with engravings. In two volumes (2 in 1) Baltimore: Joseph N. Lewis. John D. Toy, printer, [1838?] (Box 23)
  - Bible. English version of the polyglot bible, containing the old and new testaments; with the marginal readings: together with a copious and original selection of references to parallel and illustrative passages. Philadelphia: Thomas, Cowperthwait, & Co., 1839 (Box 12)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, translated from the Latin Vulgat: diligently compared with the Hebrew, Greek and other editions in divers languages the Old Testament, first published by the English College at Doway, A.D. 1609. and the New Testament, first published by the English College at Rhemes, A.D. 1582. with... first stereotype, from the fifth Dublin edition... Philadelphia: Eugene Cumminsky, 1839 (Box 36)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues: and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Baltimore: Armstrong and Berry, 1839 (Box 12)
  - Bible. Die Bibel, oder die ganze heilige schrift des alten und neuen testaments. Nach Dr. Martin Luther's uebersetzung. Zwolfte Auflage. Stereotypirt von J. Howe, Philadelphia. New York: Amerikanischen Bible=Gesllschaft, 1839 (Box 50)
  - Bible. Alexander's stereotype edition the Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments, translated from the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised: with Canne's marginal notes and references to which are added and index: and alphabetical table... Philadelphia: Stereotyped and published by C. Alexander & Co., 1839 (N.T. t.p. date 183?) (Box 24)
  - Bible. Holy Bible &c. &c. &c. with notes by Rev. Henry Stebbing A.M. M.R.S.L. London: Allan Bell and Co. and Francis Orr & Sons, GlasgowNew Testament dated 1839., 1830-1840 (Box 2)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues: and with the former translations diligently compared and revised, by his Majesty's special command. Appointed to be read in churches. Oxford: Printed at the University Press by Samuel Collingwood and co., 1840 (Box 36)
  - Bible. Holy Bible containing the old and new testaments translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. Stereotyped by L. Johnson, Philadelphia. Philadelphia: Ed. Barrington and Geo. D. Haswell, [1840?] (Date from a note by Hodge) (Box 53)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. New York: Printed by D. Fanshaw for the American Bible Society, 1841 (Box 13)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. New York: Printed by Daniel Fanshaw for the American Bible Society, 1842 (Box 12)
  - Bible. Holy Bible, containing the old and new testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised. New York: Printed by D. Fanshaw for the American Bible Society, 1843 (Box 20)
  - Bible. Pictorial bible, being the old and new testaments according to the authorized version: illustrated with more than one thousand engravings, representing the historical events, after celebrated pictures; ... New York: J.S. Redfield and Philadelphia: Thomas, Cowperthwait, & Co., and Boston: Saxton, Pierce, & Co.(Pt. Of St. Matthew missing at beg. of N.T.), 1843 (Box 36)
  - Bible. English version of the Polyglott bible, containing the old and new testaments; with the marginal readings; together with a copious and original selection of references to parallel and illustrative passages, exhibited in a manner hitherto unattempted. With Psalms in metre. Philadelphia: Wm. Rutter & Co., [1843?] (Box 36)